<?xml-stylesheet href="docster.html.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<doc>
    <copyright>dexter (c) 2007, 2008 Michael Dykman 
Free for use under version 2.0 of the Artistic License.     
http://www.opensource.org/licences/artistic-license.php</copyright>

	<title>The Case for XSL</title>
	<subtitle><![CDATA[this.changes(everything);]]></subtitle>
	<author><![CDATA[Michael Dykman <michael@dykman.org>]]></author>
		<overview>
			<para>Why XSL seems like a good idea</para>
		</overview>  <references>
    <reference>
      <title>Dexter</title>
      <summary>An introduction to dexter and it's design philosophy.</summary>
      <url>index.xml</url>
    </reference>

    <reference>
      <title>Dexter User Guide</title>
      <summary>Reference material 
      needed to use dexter and dexterity to produce XSL stylesheets</summary>
      <url>dexter-user-guide.xml</url>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Dexter API</title>

      <summary>Reference material 
      for the developer who wishes to implement their own
      descriptors, editors and path functions</summary>
      <url>dexter-api.xml</url>
    </reference>
  </references>
	<section>
		<title>The Case for XSL</title>


		<chapter>
			<title>The Objective</title>
			<para><![CDATA[
			The holy grail for back-end web development for nigh-on a
			decade has been to leverage the considerable power of XML
			and completely decouple the server application from the vagaries
			of managing the view. With the display elements out of the way,
			simple rigorous tests of application output may be more easily 
			designed and enforced.  Applications can be written more cleanly
			and more rapidly, arguable with fewer errors. To achieve this 
			Utopian state of affairs, we must first address the problem of 
			whatever does deal with the view. The solution comes back every 
			time: XSLT.  The  XSLT stylesheet allows us to format arbitrary 
			streams of XML into user-consumable documents, such as XHTML, SVG 
			or any of the host of XML-derived formats. 
			]]></para>
			<para><![CDATA[
			XSLT is a powerful and well-established mechanism 
			specified by the ]]><link url="http://www.w3c.org">W3C</link> 
			<![CDATA[ and implemented by all modern browsers.  It is designed 
            to transform arbitrary XML into other XML forms.  Turning XML 
			data into XHTML is very easily accomplished. Any reasonably 
            competent web developer can, in time, learn to manually produce 
            an	XSLT stylesheet from a given design document in a matter of hours.
			]]></para>

		</chapter>
		<chapter>
			<title>The Pros</title>
			<para><![CDATA[
			Most modern web browsers can apply the transformation 
			locally, distributing the CPU cycles the server would otherwise 
			would have to have spend.  For those clients which are not
			capable of applying transforms locally, a lightweight transform-proxy
			may be introduced, and with it, the possibility of dynamically
			binding the application's data into a larger number of output formats,
			each best suited to the proxy-client making the request. The 
			application enjoys the luxury of not caring what device we are responding
			to.  We have already put XML responders and web service frameworks into place 
			to serve those 'pure' data responses to Ajax requests and a host
			of proprietary HTTP clients; wouldn't it be nice if we could handle
			page requests from web browsers with the same simple elegance the
			web service model provides? 
			]]></para>
			<para><![CDATA[
			The current practice of serving fully
			rendered HTML pages to clients browsers has us serving all the same
			formatted markup across the network when users are browsing similarly 
			formatted pages, such as message boards, a news feed or a set of 
			profile summaries.  The actual amount of variable data in each of 
			these pages is often quite small compared to the byte-count of the fully 
			rendered page which we push out again and again. Additionally, our 
			application typically integrates with a template manager to render our 
			application-derived data sets into an HTML stream. 
      ]]></para>
      <para><![CDATA[
            The templates themselves typically represent fragments of HTML and tend to 
            multiply as more sophisticated screen flows and visual designs are developed.
            For front-end developers, It can also be difficult if not impossible to simply
            view them through a standard web browser for visual feedback without putting 
            them though the application process.  
		]]></para>
		<para><![CDATA[
			A word about template managers: while we have been using them very 
			effectively for many years to deliver text-based content, the nature 
			of the game has been refined in recent years.  While 
			[[insert your favorite template manager here]] is an effective 
			engine/tool for manipulating strings, often in highly imaginative and 
			sophisticated ways, the fact is, we are no longer in the business of 
			delivering strings.  We are now in the business of delivering Documents,
			whether XHTML, RSS or arbitrary structured data, it's all W3C-compliant 
			XML. 
			]]></para>
			<para><![CDATA[
			Producing Documents with a string manipulation tool is about as effective
			as bringing a knife to a gun-fight. The templates and HTML fragments become
            a maintenance and version control challenge unto themselves as 
			they must be maintained with reference to a ever-evolving design document.
            It certainly can be done and done very effectively; after all, pretty much
			the entire dynamic web is currently deployed in such a manner. But the 
			fact remains that such productions can be convoluted and error-prone.  
			A higher-level approach would be welcome.    
			]]></para>

			<para><![CDATA[
			For the developer and the architect, adopting an XSLT-based delivery 
			model offers some very attractive features. The application only needs to deliver 
			structured data to the client instead of the fully-formed document. 
			Template manager integration is no longer a necessity.  You are spared 
			the expense of rendering out fully marked-up XHTML to many clients.  
			Instead, the client uses it's own CPU to produce layout. The page layout, 
			being encapsulated in an XSLT file, needs only to be fetched once by the 
			browser, compiled once and then used repeatedly by the client to render 
			similar pages.  The network is spared the expense of retransmitting the 
			formatting details more than once which can significantly reduce the number
			of bytes the application needs to transmit. Nearly every modern server-side 
			language or application framework provides elegant, transparent means for 
			transforming application data representations into arbitrary 
			structured XML, suitable for transmission.  The output of your applications 
			may now be rigorously defined much more easily.  Any given application 
			response can be associated with an xml-schema or a DTD.  Continuous 
			integration can leverage the fact and validate application responses
			with greater accuracy as these tests are now isolated from the effects
			of constantly evolving visual design changes. 
			]]></para>
		</chapter>
		<chapter>
			<title>The Cons</title>
			<para><![CDATA[
			In many ways, XML has  been a boon to distributed application
			developers in hundreds, if not thousands, of ways.  Conceptually, it is simple,
			regular, easy to manipulate, powerful in it's expressive capabilities and amply
			supported by nearly all modern languages. Yet it is not always elegant. 
            In order to accomplish the most mundane tasks, productions which can be expressed
            in a few words or symbols, many lines of application code are often needed. 
            XSLT is a prime example of this. For all of it's expressive power, it is extremely verbose.
			]]></para>
			<para><![CDATA[
			The real challenge of current XSLT deployment strategies is in QA and change 
			management. Design documents are generally produced by naive web designers who, 
			for the most part, are decidedly non-technical. In real-world practice, after 
			the initial stylesheet has been produced (or while it is still in process), 
			change requests begin to pour in. These changes may be small and, with some 
			experience, our intrepid developer is able to edit those changes directly into the 
			work in progress. Inevitably, larger changes will be introduced, possibly causing
			our stylesheet author to lose place or have to start over.  Data-driven or not, 
			XSLT productions are still very much procedural code and requires a similar 
			level of discipline to maintain. Even under the best of circumstances, manual XSLT
			production is an error-prone process requiring rigorous scrutiny from QA after the fact.
			This can be frustrating in the face of impatient clients who do not and can not
			understand why their desire for immediate satisfaction needs to be tempered
			'for technical reasons'. 
			]]></para>
			<para><![CDATA[
			For the manager of this process, there is another side to the story. 
			Having largely freed the back-end systems from worrying about how any given data 
			set renders, new services can be developed and tested more rapidly and with greater
			accuracy engendering potentially reduced costs.  On the other hand, any changes to
            the pages which
			end-users will see in their browsers are now bottle-necked by the few resources 
			available who understand XSLT; particularly, those few who are familiar with
			the specific structures of such stylesheets as have already been deployed.   
			]]></para>
		</chapter>

		<chapter>
			<title>The Solution</title>
			<para><![CDATA[
			If XSLT production could be simplified, made more accessible and less error-prone, 
			the down-side could be mitigated.  Ideally, if XSLT production could be accomplished
			as part of a build process that flows directly from the design document, that risk
			disappears. That is precisely what ]]><link url="dexter-user-guide.xml">dexter</link> 
            is designed to do.
			</para>
		</chapter>
	</section>
</doc>
